Dun and Bradstreet, Inc. Collection of Small Business Ledgers
Dun and Bradstreet, Inc. Collection of Small Business Ledgers
1754-1955
Dun and Bradstreet, inc.
25 linear ft. (208 ledgers)
Collection of ledgers from a wide range of small businesses based in the Northeastern United States, from Philadelphia to Old Town, Maine, including many in New Jersey. Business areas represented range from banking and butchers to taverns and wagon-makers.
148955
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Dun and Bradstreet, Inc. Collection of Small Business Ledgers consists of ledgers and account books and a small amount of miscellaneous material.
Ledgers and account books comprise the majority of the collection. This series contains business accounts dating mostly from the late 1700's through the mid-1800's. All of the firms represented here were American, with the exception of Ledgers 133 and 134. Most of these firms were based in the North-east, stretching from Philadelphia to Old Town, Maine, and reaching as far inland as Utica and Phelps, New York. Many of the firms were based in New Jersey.
Since most (if not all) of these firms are no longer extant, the ledgers have been arranged not by name of business, but by type. Business types represented here are: Banking, Blacksmithing, Butcher, Brick-Making, Carting, Coal Dealer, Construction, Distiller, Druggist, Dyeing, Egg Dealer, Family Estate, Farms, Farm Products, Fertilizer, Fish, General Stores, Hat-Making, Importing, Insurance, Iron Works, Lawyers, Lumber Yard, Metals Dealer, Milling, Patent Office, Pedlar, Personal Expense Accounts, Post Office, Real Estate, Shipping, Shoe-Makers, Taverns, Taxes, Taylor, Town Records, Tug Boats, Wagon-Maker, Weather Diaries, Workmen's Time Books, and General.
Although some business records for all of these firms have survived here, the names and locations for many of them have been lost.
It is important to note the difference between "day books" and "journals" as opposed to "ledgers." Day books and journals are arranged from beginning to end chronologically. Ledgers, on the other hand, are arranged into separate business accounts, and chronologically only within each account. Many ledgers contain an alphabetical index for these separate accounts.
The Miscellaneous series contains three items: a facsimile of a 1765 non-importation resolution, an old undated map of the mid-western states, and the 1926 typescript of a history of an early railroad, with photographs of early steam engines.
Of particular interest are the news clippings pasted into Ledgers 10 and 21, and the Victorian-era cartoons and doodles in the back pages of Ledger 131.
Arrangement of the Collection
Books are arranged in alphabetical order by business area, and within that chronologically.
Subject and Genre Headings
Business and Industry; Dun and Bradstreet, inc. -- Archives.; Accounting -- Books of account.; Agriculture -- Accounting.; Banks and banking -- Accounting.; Blacksmiths -- Accounting.; Brickmakers -- Accounting.; Butchers -- Accounting.; Coal trade -- Accounting.; Construction industry -- Accounting.; Distilleries -- Accounting.; Dye industry -- Accounting.; Egg trade -- Accounting.; Fertilizer industry -- Accounting.; Fish trade -- Accounting.; General stores -- Accounting.; Grain -- Milling.; Taverns (Inns) -- Accounting.; Insurance companies -- Accounting.; Iron foundries -- Accounting.; Lumber trade -- Accounting.; Metal trade -- Accounting.; Millinery -- Accounting.; Peddlers and peddling -- Accounting.; Pharmacists -- Accounting.; Practice of law -- Accounting.; Real estate business -- Accounting.; Ship chandlers -- Accounting.; Shoemakers -- Accounting.; Small business -- Accounting.; Small business -- Atlantic States.; Small business -- New England.; Account books.; Daybooks.; Diaries.; Ledgers (account books)
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Acquired from Dun and Bradstreet, Inc. in 1955, plus purchases of similiar materials, to 1970.
Inventory
- Ledgers and account books
  - Banking
    - U.S. Bank, New Jersey
      - Abstract of Creditors, 1797-1800 (Volume 1)
      - Stock Ledger, 1797-1817 (Volume 2)
      - Loan Office Journal, Interest Account, 1801-1810 (Volume 3)
    - Pamphlets, Bank of Maryland, 1816-1835 (Volume 4)
    - Profit and Loss Accounts, Wood & Van Sant, 1882-1891 (Volume 5)
    - Banking Journal, Philadelphia, 1883-1884 (Volume 6)
  - Blacksmithing
    - Journal, Nathan Matteson, 1797-1804 (Volume 7)
    - Ledger, Ephram Page, 1820-1826 (Volume 8)
    - Ledger, 1823-1827 (Volume 9)
    - Ledger, 1831-1839; also contains news clippings (Volume 10)
    - Parsons, Phelps, New York
      - Day Book, 1831-1834 (Volume 11)
      - Day Books, 1835-1837 (Volume 12)
    - C.F. Adams, Bellows Falls, Vermont
      - Ledger, 1840-1845 (Volume 13)
      - Day Book, 1863-1865 (Volume 14)
    - Day Book, Stephen C. Larabee, 1842-1845 (Volume 15)
    - John S. Heston, Trenton, New Jersey
      - Ledgers, 1842-1849 (Volume 16)
      - Ledgers, 1850-1856 (Volume 17)
    - Day Book, Greensville, New Jersey, 1849-1873 (Volume 18)
    - Warren F. Westfall, Beemerville, New Jersey
      - Ledger, 1849-1854 (Volume 19)
      - Ledger, 1857-1892 (Volume 20)
      - Day Book with clippings, 1851-1855; contains news clippings of a serialized novel, The Follett Curs, printed by The Toledo Blade in 1889. (Volume 21)
      - Day Book, 1857-1863 (Volume 22)
      - Day Book, 1863-1865 (Volume 23)
    - Day Book, Debtors' Record, 1858-1864 (Volume 24)
  - Butcher
    - Day Book, 1834-1836 (Volume 25)
  - Brick-Making
    - Journal, Watson Firebrick Company, Perth Amboy, New Jersey, 1886-1897 (Volume 26)
    - Candee, Smith & Howland Co., Masons' Building Material
      - Letter Book, 1900-1923 (Volume 27)
      - Letter Book, 1923-1942 (Volume 28)
  - Carting
    - A.H.Tyrell & Son, Perth Amboy, New Jersey, 1868-1877 (Volume 29)
  - Coal dealer
    - James T. Watson, Perth Amboy, New Jersey, 1886-1916 (Volume 30)
  - Construction
    - Ledger, Thomas Taylor, 1803-1806 (Volume 31)
    - Minutes Book, Amsterdam Bridge Company, 1821 (Volume 32)
    - Ledger, Construction Materials, 1852-1853 (Volume 33)
  - Distiller
    - Isaac Howell, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania
      - Journal, 1759-1767 (Volume 34)
      - Ledger, 1767-1790 (Volume 35)
  - Druggist
    - Jeremiah Emlen, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania
      - Ledger, 1797-1815 (Volume 36)
      - Letter Book, 1810-1826 (Volume 37)
      - Day Book, 1815 (Volume 38)
      - Day Book, 1815-1819 (Volume 39)
      - Day Book, 1819-1823 (Volume 40)
      - Letter Book, 1822-1826 (Volume 41)
  - Dyeing
    - Ledger, 1808-1812; 1843-1844 (Volume 42)
    - Day Book, Ornsby, Daniel & Co., 1825-1833 (Volume 43)
  - Egg Dealer
    - S.S. Long, New York City
      - Journal, 1858-1859 (Volume 44)
      - Journal, 1861-1862 (Volume 45)
      - Journal, 1866-1868 (Volume 46)
      - Journal, 1873-1887 (Volume 47)
      - Ledger, 1863-1879 (Volume 48)
  - Family Estate
    - Ledger, Botts Family Estate, 1817-1848 (Volume 49)
    - Journal, George Conant Estate, 1836-1853 (Volume 50)
  - Farms
    - Josiah Bacon, Newton, Massachusetts, 1804-1810 (Volume 51)
    - Peter Voorheis, Blawenburgh, New Jersey
      - Journal, 1812-1848 (Volume 52)
      - Estate Books, 1820; 1823,; 1835-1836; 3 volumes (Volume 53)
      - Ledger, 1832-1838 (Volume 54)
    - Day Books, 1828-1833 (Volume 55)
    - Journal, 1830-1846 (Volume 56)
    - Day Book, 1841-1856 (Volume 57)
    - Journal, Westhampton, N.Y., 1844-1864 (Volume 58)
  - Farm Products
    - George Hoffman, Asbury, New Jersey
      - Day Book, 1858-1862 (Volume 59)
      - Account Book, 1860 (Volume 60)
      - Day Book, 1875-1880 (Volume 61)
      - Ledger, 1875-1880 (Volume 62)
  - Fertilizer
    - Treasurer's ledger and stock ledger, New Jersey Fertilizer Company, Middletown, New Jersey, 1856-1861 (Volume 63)
  - Fish
    - Day Book, Totten's Landing, Staten Island, 1844-184? (Volume 64)
  - General Stores
    - Day Book, Boston and Weathersfield, 1760-1762 (Volume 65)
    - Day Book, Hanover, 1773-1774 (Volume 66)
    - Abner Loring, Hingham, Massachusetts
      - Journal, 1783-1785 (Volume 67)
      - Journal, 1783-1784; 1788-1789,; 1823,; 1834-1835 (Volume 68)
    - Zebadiah Tracy, Windham
      - Ledger, 1784-1789 (Volume 69)
      - Ledger, 1788-1794 (Volume 70)
      - Ledger, 1793-1801 (Volume 71-a)
    - Ledger, 1792-1796 (Volume 71-b)
    - Joshua Atwater, Wallingford, Connecticut
      - Day Book, 1793-1794 (Volume 72)
      - Day Book, 1794-1795 (Volume 73)
      - Day Book, 1797-1807 (Volume 74)
      - Day Book, 1800-1801 (Volume 75)
      - Day Book, 1803-1805 (Volume 76)
      - Day Book, 1821-1824 (Volume 77)
      - Ledger, 1793-1813 (Volume 78)
      - Ledger, 1799-1816 (Volume 79)
      - Ledger, 1809-1834 (Volume 80)
    - Journal, New York, 1814-1820 (Volume 81)
    - Day Book, Elisha Blin, Whitehall, N.Y., 1816-1828 (Volume 82)
    - Day Book, White Plains, 1818 (Volume 83)
    - Day Book, Pine Island, New York, 1821-1823 (Volume 84)
    - Day Book, Pine Island, New York, 1823-1824 (Volume 85)
    - Journal, William Chadwick, New York, 1823-1830 (Volume 86)
    - Ledger, New Jersey, 1824-1826 (Volume 87)
    - W. Smith & Co., Farmerville, New York
      - Day Book, 1824 (Volume 88)
      - Day Book, 1826-1827 (Volume 89)
    - Nathan Satterthwaite, Crosswicks, New Jersey
      - Day Book, 1825-1827 (Volume 90)
      - Day Book, 1827-1831 (Volume 91)
    - Day Book, John M. Ames, New Haven, Conn., 1831-1832 (Volume 92)
    - Lathrop, Potkin & Wait, Burlington, Vermont
      - Ledger, 1836-1881 (Volume 93)
      - Ledger, 1839-1841 (Volume 94)
      - Day Book, 1839-1840 (Volume 95)
      - Day Book, 1839-1841 (Volume 96)
    - Crowell & Freeman, Perth Amboy, New Jersey
      - Day Book, 1837 (Volume 97)
      - Day Book, 1838 (Volume 98)
      - Day Book, 1841 (Volume 99)
      - Day Book, 1851 (Volume 100)
      - Ledger, 1839-1841 (Volume 101)
    - Day Book, Woodville, New York, 1838-1839 (Volume 102)
    - Journal, Winthrop & Potwin, Burlington, Vermont, 1839-1843 (Volume 103)
    - Ledger, Zebadiah Wills, 1841-1842 (Volume 104)
    - Journal, Gilbert H. Cooper, 1845-1848 (Volume 105)
    - Day Book, Walter Dickerson, Woodville, 1846-1850 (Volume 106)
    - Day Book, Epping, 1850 (Volume 107-a)
    - S.S. Denton, Vernon, New Jersey
      - Journal, 1847 (Volume 107-b)
      - Ledger, 1854-1858 (Volume 108)
      - Ledger, 1870-1879 (Volume 109)
      - Ledger, 1882-1888 (Volume 110)
      - Journal, 1870-1877 (Volume 111)
      - Journal, 1877-1880 (Volume 112)
      - Journal, 1881-1895 (Volume 113)
      - Journal, 1890-1891 (Volume 114)
    - M.P. Wadleigh, Old Town, Maine
      - Ledger, 1850 (Volume 115)
      - Ledger, 1856-1857 (Volume 116)
      - Ledger, 1860-1865 (Volume 117)
      - Journal, 1868 (Volume 118)
    - Journal, 1857-1860 (Volume 119)
    - C.B. Stout, Centerville, New Jersey
      - Day Book, 1858-1859 (Volume 120)
      - Day Book, 1861 (Volume 121)
      - Day Book, 1871-1872 (Volume 122)
      - Ledger, 1862-1867 (Volume 123)
    - Journal, South Brunswick, New Jersey, 1866-1877 (Volume 124)
    - John J. Backster, Lafayette, New Jersey
      - Ledger, 1870-1875 (Volume 125)
      - Day Book, 1875-1877 (Volume 126)
      - Journal, 1881-1883 (Volume 127)
      - Journal, 1885-1886 (Volume 128)
      - Journal, 1886-1888 (Volume 129)
      - Journal, 1888-1890 (Volume 130)
  - Hat-Making
    - Ledger, with cartoons and drawings added (circa 1890), 1767-1777; 1890 (Volume 131)
  - Importing
    - Letter-book, Frank H. Maynard, 1868-1870 (Volume 132)
  - Insurance
    - Liverpool & London & Globe Insurance Co., New Jersey office
      - Insurance account journal, 1921-1925 (Volume 133)
      - Insurance account journal, 1928-1937 (Volume 134)
  - Iron Works
    - Dry Dock Iron Works
      - Accounts Receivable and Payable, 1853-1859 (Volume 135)
      - Accounts Receivable and Payable, 1859-1866 (Volume 136)
      - Cash Book, 1859-1862 (Volume 137)
      - Time Book, 1856-1862 (Volume 138)
      - New York, Iron Foundry, 1956 (Volume 139)
  - Lawyers
    - Thomas Lee
      - Ledger, 1806-1815 (Volume 140)
      - Ledger, 1809-1810 (Volume 141)
    - J.S. Mitchell, 1829-1833 (Volume 142)
    - Record of Court Cases, Burlington Co., N.J., 1839-1840 (Volume 143)
    - Ledger, New Jersey, 1840-1850 (Volume 144)
    - Record of Court Cases, Somerset Co., N.J., 1845-1850 (Volume 145)
  - Lumber Yard
    - Philadelphia, Pa.
      - Journal, 1817-1819 (Volume 146)
      - Journal, 1819-1822 (Volume 147)
      - Journal, 1820-1823 (Volume 148)
  - Metals Dealer
    - J.S. Underhill
      - Receipts, 1862-1866 (Volume 149)
      - Store Room Book, 1863-1865 (Volume 150)
      - Cash Book, 1866 (Volume 151)
  - Milling
    - Samuel Wetherill, Grain and Saw Mills, Pennsylvania
      - General, 1816-1823 (Volume 152)
      - Wetherill Estate and Mill Accounts, 1816-1829; 1820-1823 (Volume 153)
    - Stoutsburg Mills, Flour Milling Ledger, 1817-1819 (Volume 154)
  - Patent Office
    - Pamphlets, 1817-1830 (Volume 155)
  - Pedlar
    - Butler, Brooms, Household Items, 1823-1824 (Volume 156)
  - Personal Expense Accounts
    - Receipt Book, Stephen Thorne, New York, 1799-1808 (Volume 157)
    - M. Houpt, Philadelphia, Pa., 1806-1809; 1827-1838 (Volume 158)
    - Account Book, Cold Spring, N.Y., 1818-1823 (Volume 159)
    - Receipt Book, John L. Graham, New York, 1823-1830 (Volume 160)
    - Receipt Book, Benjamin Grimm, accounts in German, 1824-1854 (Volume 161)
    - Cash journal, 1852-1860 (Volume 162)
    - Journal, Frank H. Maynard, 1868-1870 (Volume 163)
  - Post Office
    - Reports, Port Elizabeth, New Jersey, 1840-1842 (Volume 164)
  - Real Estate
    - Ledger, Horatio Seymour, Utica, New York, 1849-1873 (Volume 165)
    - Abstracts of Titles, 1854-1855 (Volume 166)
  - Shipping
    - Ledger, Daniel Wright, Voyage Accounts, 1754-1760 (Volume 167)
    - Day Book, William Breck, Ships Accounts, 1781-1792 (Volume 168)
    - Sag Harbor, New York, Ship Yard, Chandler
      - Day Book, 1806-1820 (Volume 169)
      - Day Book, 1810-1812 (Volume 170)
      - Day Book, 1820-1821 (Volume 171)
    - Chandler
      - Journal, 1812-1830 (Volume 172)
      - Ledger, 1819-1827 (Volume 173)
    - Ship Barreda Brothers
      - Shipping journal, 1854-1860 (Volume 174)
      - Shipping journal, 1857-1860 (Volume 175)
    - Chandler, Perth Amboy, New Jersey, Tug Boats
      - Ledger, 1886-1889 (Volume 176)
      - Ledger, 1889-1892 (Volume 177)
    - Ship's Log, F.H. Prince, 1894-1896 (Volume 178-a)
  - Shoe-Makers
    - Day Book, Timothy Gaylord, Norfolk, 1772-1776 (Volume 178-b)
    - Day Book, Islip, New York, 1810-1847 (Volume 178-c)
    - Day Book, Abram Bloodgood, 1836-1840 (Volume 178-d)
  - Taverns
    - William D. Jewell
      - Ledger, 1806-1823 (Volume 179)
      - Ledger, 1859-1890 (Volume 180)
      - Day Book, 1806-1810 (Volume 181)
      - Day Book, 1826-1838 (Volume 182)
  - Taxes
    - New Jersey, James Mott, Treasurer
      - Disbursements, Treasurer's Day Book, 1780-1803 (Volume 183)
      - Loan Office Certificates, Interest Journal, 1784-1790 (Volume 184)
      - Loan Office Certificates, 1790-1795 (Volume 185)
      - Revenue Tax Ledger, 1785-1803 (Volume 186)
  - Taylor
    - Ledger, 1753-1755 (Volume 187)
    - Journal, New York, 1771-1778 (Volume 188)
  - Town Records
    - Ledger, Chesterfield, New Jersey, 1773-1847 (Volume 189)
  - Tug Boats
    - Day Book, West Troy, N.Y., 1858 (Volume 190)
      See also Chandler, Perth Amboy, New Jersey, Tug Boats (Ledgers 176 and 177)
  - Wagon-Maker
    - Account Book, 1819 (Volume 191)
  - Weather Diaries
    - Daily Calendar, 1859 (Volume 192)
    - Daily Calendar, 1860 (Volume 193)
  - Workmen's Time Book
    - Overtime Journal, 1862-1863 (Volume 194)
  - General Ledgers
    - Receipt Book, Josiah Langdale Coates, 1769-1794 (Volume 195)
    - Ledger, Unidentified, 1837 (Volume 196-a)
    - Journal, Commission Merchant, New Canaan, Connecticut, 1837 (Volume 196-b)
    - Receipt Book, William C. Smith Co., Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, 1844-1856 (Volume 197)
    - Ledger, McLaughlin Brothers, 1897-1900 (Volume 198)
    - Journal, Untitled, 1940-1955 (Volume 199)
- Miscellaneous
  - Non-importation resolution, Philadelphia, 1765; facsimile (Volume 200)
  - Maps, Illinois, Iowa, Kansas, New Mexico, Oklahoma (Volume 201)
  - Railroad history typescript, The Evolution of Transportation and Early History of America's First Railroad by C.N. Esender, Los Angeles, 1926 (Volume 202)